这是我们之前介绍的串行链路逆动力学表达式
Here is the expression we introduced earlier for the inverse dynamics of a serial link
机器人机械手以矩阵形式表示。我们现在有兴趣考虑这种影响
robot manipulator expressed in matrix form. We are interested now to consider the effect
重力。重力是即使机器人不移动也会作用于机器人的力。所以我们
of gravity. Gravity is the force that acts on the robot even if it's not moving. So we
可以消除与关节加速度和关节速度成比例的项。
can eliminate the terms that are proportional to the joint acceleration and the joint velocity.
这就是这个术语。术语G.这表示重力扭矩
It's just this term on the end here. The term G. This represents the gravity torque that's
作用于机器人机械手的关节。这是抵消重力和扭矩的扭矩
acting on the joints of the robot manipulator. It's the torque that counteracts gravity and
阻止手臂在自重下塌陷。
stops the arm from collapsing under its own weight.
这里我们再次提供了我们的2连杆机器人的符号模型。而我要做的是
Here again we have a symbolic model of our 2 link robot. And what I'm going to do is
使用方法gravload告诉我作用在关节上的扭矩
to use the method gravload which tells me the torque that is acting on the joints of
机器人。gravload的参数是关节角度。我传入一个包含的向量
the robot. The arguments to gravload are the joint angles. I pass in a vector which contains
Q1和Q2;这个象征性的联合变量。这是重力的表达
Q1 and Q2; this symbolic joint variables. And here's the expression for gravity which
作用于机器人的关节。我们看到关节1的术语是相当的
is acting on the joints of the robot. And we see that the term for joint 1 is quite
因为关节2的表达稍微短一些。
long where as the expression for joint 2 is a little bit shorter.
我们可以看到该表达式包含链接长度A1和的运动学参数
We can see that this expression contains a kinematic parameters the link lengths A1 and
A2。质量中心C1和C2的位置，两个关节的质量M1和
A2. The positions of the centres of mass C1 and C2, the masses of the two joints M1 and
M2。我们可以看到这里有很多cos和sine术语。
M2. And we can see that there are a lot of cos and sine terms in here.
到目前为止，我们已经谈到机器人的力量，仅仅是因为它自身的重量。但是有用的
So far we've talked about the forces on the robot just due to its own weight. But a useful
机器人还必须能够携带有效载荷。从这里挑选一个物体并将其放下
robot also has to be able to carry a payload. Pick an object up from here and put it down
在那边。很明显，机器人链条中的最后一个环节必须保持有效载荷。
over there. So clearly the last link in the chain of the robot has to hold the payload.
但是沿着链条传播到机器人的底部。每个关节都在
But that propagates down the chain towards the base of the robot. Every joint in the
机器人必须帮助保持有效载荷，以防止它被重力拉下。
robot has to help hold up the payload to stop it being pulled down by the force of gravity.
那么有效载荷的影响是什么？那么每个关节都有最大可能的扭矩。所以
So what's the effect of payload? Well every joint has got a maximum possible torque. So
让我们想象一下，我们在机器人的末端有一个有效载荷，我们不断增加它的质量。
let's imagine that we have a payload on the end of the robot and we keep increasing it's mass.
我们可以计算每个关节需要施加的扭矩以便保持
We can work out the torque that each of the Joints needs to exert in order to hold up
有效载荷。随着我们增加有效载荷的质量，最终我们会找到那个
that payload. As we increase the mass of the payload, eventually we will find that one
关节将达到其扭矩限制，它将变得超载。这是最大有效载荷
joint will hit its torque limit it will become overloaded. And that's the maximum payload
机器人可以握住。
that the robot can hold.
现在我们知道重力扭矩是机器人配置的函数。
Now we know that the gravity torque is the function of the configuration of the robot.
如果一个机器人持有10公斤，可能会有一些配置特别是在哪里
If a robot's holding 10 kg there might be some configurations particularly where the
10公斤靠近机器人的底座，在那里可以容纳特定的有效载荷。
10 kg is close to the base of the robot where it's possible to hold that particular payload.
但是，如果机器人的手臂完全伸展，它可能无法保持这种特性
But if the robot has got its arm fully stretched, it may not be able to hold that particular
有效载荷。因此，机器人的最大有效负载是扭矩能力的函数
payload. So the maximum payload of the robot is a function of the torque capabilities of
电机但它也是机器人配置的一个功能。
the motors but it is also a function of the configuration of the robot.
我将回到我们的2连杆机器人的数值模型，我加载使用
I am going to go back to a numerical model of our 2 link robot and I load that using
脚本mdl_twolink。
the script mdl_twolink.
我现在要使用gravload方法计算机器人关节的重力负荷。
I'm going to now compute the gravity load on the robot's joints using the gravload method.
我将为关节角度0和0计算出来。这就是我们得到的结果。在
I'm going to compute that for joint angle 0 and 0. And this is the result we get. In
事实上我们使用递归Newton-Euler算法得到的结果相同。
fact the same result we got a little bit earlier using the recursive Newton-Euler algorithm.
实际上，重力加载本身是基于递归的Newton-Euler算法。
In fact gravity load itself is based on the recursive Newton-Euler algorithm.
我们来看看我们机器人的配置。我们打算用它来联合
Let's just have a look at a configuration of our robot. We're going to plot it for joint
角度0和0，这就是它的样子。现在我们假设我们把机器人放进去了
angles 0 and 0 and this is what it looks like. Now let's imagine that we put the robot into
不同的配置。让我们使第一个关节角度等于2弧度的PI
a different configuration. Let's make the first joint angle equal to PI on 2 radians
或90度。但现在我们的机器人指向上方。
or 90 degrees. But now our robot is pointing straight upwards.
那么在这种情况下我们怎么看待关节上的重力负荷呢？嗯，这很容易
So what do we think the gravity load on the joints would be in this case? Well it's easy
足以搞清楚。我们使用twolink对象，gravload方法，我们传入关节
enough to figure out. We use the twolink object, the gravload method and we pass in the joint
角度，PI在2和0上。我们看到关节上的重力负荷几乎相等
angles, PI on 2 and 0. And we see that the gravity load on the joints is almost equal
这里零或一些轻微的数值误差。这是10到减去14.这是什么
to zero or some slight numerical error here. It's 10 to the minus 14. And this is what
我们期望，因为在这种特殊配置中，接头不需要施加任何扭矩
we expect because in this particular configuration, the joints don't need to exert any torque
完全可以让机器人直线上升。事实上，机器人在直立状态下保持平衡
at all to hold the robot straight up. The robot is in fact balancing in an upright
组态。它不稳定，但不需要任何关节扭矩来维持这一点
configuration. It's not stable but it doesn't require any joint torque to maintain this
确切的配置。
exact configuration.
现在我们来看看对有效载荷的影响。我可以将负载添加到我的机器人对象中
Now we're going to look at the effect on payload. I can add a payload to my robot object very
容易。这是我的机器人对象，我使用了有效载荷方法，我将添加一个
easily. Here is my robot object and I used the payload method and I'm going to add a
1千克有效载荷，它将被放置在相对于坐标0,0,0的位置
1 kg payload, and it's going to be placed at the coordinate 0, 0, 0 with respect to
链接2坐标框架。
the link 2 coordinate frame.
所以它实际上是在链接2的末尾。机器人现在有一个有效载荷
So it's actually going to be right on the end of link 2. The robot now has a payload
现在我要计算机器人在配置时的重力负荷
and now I'm going to compute the gravity load for the robot when it's in the configuration
0,0。因此，手臂伸直，水平伸展。
0,0. So that's with the arm stretched out straight and horizontally.
现在我们看到关节，关节1和关节2上的扭矩增加了。那就是
Now we see that the torque on the joints, on joint 1 and joint 2 is increased. And that's
因为机器人试图在这种相当笨拙的配置中保持1公斤的负载。
because the robot is trying to hold a 1 kg load in this rather awkward configuration.
所以机器人关节必须尽可能地努力才能保持
So the robot joints are going to have to work about as hard as they can in order to keep
从机器人的末端拉下1公斤。
that 1 kg from pulling the end of the robot down.
我们现在来看一个复杂的机器人模型。我们介绍了PUMA560机器人的模型。
Let's look now at a complex robot model. We introduce a model for the PUMA 560 robot.
你可以看到我们的工作空间中有一个名为P560的新变量，它是另一个变量
And you can see that there is a new variable in our workspace called P560, it’s another
串行链接对象，可以描述机器人操纵器。
serial link object which can describe a robot manipulator.
我们将为这个机器人使用相同的gravload方法。对于任何更好的事情之一
We're going to use the same gravload method for this robot. And for one of anything better
我将把所有等于零的关节角度放入。这就是重力负荷
I'm going to put in joint angles all equal to zero. And this is what the gravity load
好像。现在我们可以看到PUMA机器人在该特定配置中的样子。
looks like. Now we can see what the PUMA robot looks like in that particular configuration.
0,0,0,0,0,0和具有全零关节角配置的PUMA机器人看起来像
0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0. And PUMA robot with a all zero joint angle configuration looks like
这个。上臂是水平的，下臂是垂直的。这些是联合
this. The upper arm is horizontal and the lower arm is vertical. And these are the joint
要求这样做的扭矩。
torques that are required to do that.
工具箱机器人对象具有很多功能，是我们可以做到的事情之一
The toolbox robot object has got a lot of capabilities and one of the things we could
做的是改变重力加速度。我们将其更改为0,0,9.81，其中
do is to change gravitational acceleration. And we change that to 0, 0, 9.81, which
是名义地球的引力，将除以6，因为这是重力在月球上的重力。
is nominal earth’s gravity, going to divide by 6 because that's what the gravity is on the moon.
现在我们可以看到机器人的重力负荷，因为它在月球上，它是重力
Now we can see the gravity load on the robot, given that it's on the moon, it's the gravity
加载功能。然后我再次将关节角放入六个零。在这里，我们看到了什么
load function. And I put in the joint angles six zeros again. And here we see what the
重力负荷，这个PUMA机器人的关节上的重力扭矩将是它在月球上工作。
gravity load, gravity torques on the joints of this PUMA robot would be if it was working on the moon.